Finding Aid for the Livingston Gearhart Papers, 1933-1997
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
- Additional personal documents, 1935-1974, VII.; Folders 109-113
  - Marriage certificate for Livingston and Pamela Gearhart, 25 November 1955, 2 items (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Appointment papers, Music Department, University at Buffalo, 1955-1974, 34 items (Box 2, Folder 113)
- Contracts for scores and recordings, 1945-1981, VIII.; Folders 114-124
  Arranged as received with folder titles and contents retained.
  Some contracts accompanied by correspondence or additional descriptions.
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Vocal, Fred Waring choral arrangements, 1949-1951, 6 items (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Vocal collections, 1955-1962, 5 items (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Orchestra, 1962-1976, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Band, 1955-1965, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Vocal singles, 1955, 16 items (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Single vocals, 1956-1959, 17 items (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: revision for collections, vocal singles, exclusivity contract, 1960-1966, 25 items (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Vocals, 1970-1976, 11 items (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: 2-piano, 1949-1978, 4 items (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Shawnee Press contracts: Sessions, 1945-1965, 6 items (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Omni Sound, Inc. contracts, 1978-1981, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - ASCAP contracts and correspondence, 1959-1997, 12 items (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Copyright assignment for Gearhart arrangement of Star spangled banner, February 14 2002, 1 item (Box 2, Folder 126)
- Inscribed texts, 1947-1988, IX.; Folder 127-128
  Chronologically arranged.
  - What is life? The physical aspect of the living cell by Erwin Schrödinger, 1946, 1 item (Box 2, Folder 127)
    Published by Cambridge Unbiversity Press/Macmillan
    Inscribed by Livingston Gearhart indicating the book was a gift from Goddard Lieberson.
  - 3 for Bedroom C by Goddard Lieberson, 1947, 1 item (Box 2, Folder 128)
    Published by Doubleday and Co.
    Inscribed to Virginia and Livingston from the author.
  - Music for Mischa, 1988, 1 item (Box 2, Folder 129)
    Program booklet for concerts presented October 2 and 23, and December 4, 1988 in the Gindi Auditorium at the University of Judaism, Los Angeles, California.
    Inscribed by Mischa Schneider's wife, June.
- Additional writings and artwork, 1939-1993, X.; Folder 130-140
  Various manuscript, typescript and printed writings by Livingston Gearhart.
  Roughly categorized by topics.
  - Composers, 1993, undated, 6 leaves (Box 3, Folder 130)
    Composers mentioned include Stravinsky, Barber, Menotti, Dupré, Ravel, Couperin, and Bach.
    Manuscript notes.
  - Geophysical variables and behavior: XXXIII. Onsets of historical and contemporary poltergeist episodes occurred with sudden increases in geomagnetic activity, 1986, 4 pages (Box 3, Folder 131)
    Offprint of article co-written with M. A. Persinger, published in Perceptual and motor skills.
  - Notes on hearing, undated, 9 leaves (Box 3, Folder 132)
    Manuscript and typescript notes.
  - Notes on the paranormal and other issues, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Notes on Robert Motherwell, undated, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Notes on Stravinsky's Firebird and Petrouschka, circa 1939, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 135)
    Manuscript notes accompanied by letter from Virginia Waring to Pamela Gearhart, and letter from Pamela to Martha Gearhart Schermerhorn.
  - Personal history, circa 1970-1992, 25 leaves (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Piano pedagogy, undated, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 137)
    Typescript notes.
  - Proposed plan for a school of music, undated, 21 leaves (Box 3, Folder 138)
    Typescript accompanied by note from Bea Long.
  - Recollections, circa 1970-1993, 17 leaves (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Artworks, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 140)
    Sketches and drawings by Livingston Gearhart, chiefly in pencil.
- Additional correspondence, 1936-2006, XI.; Folder 141-179
  Includes both personal and business correspondence.
  Alphabetically arranged by correspondent surname, with unidentified names following, and a closing sequence of collected correspondence regarding Gearhart publications.
  - Both, Ernst E.: November 17, 1986, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Brookbank, Ricki: undated, October 5, 1946, 3 items (Box 3, Folder 142)
    Manuscript and typescript.
  - Farmer, Ernest: 1981-1999, 4 items (5 leaves) (Box 3, Folder 143)
    Includes correspondence from Livingston Gearhart to Ernie and Majorie Farmer, from Ernie to Livingston, and Ernie to Pamela Gearhart.
  - G. Schirmer, Inc.: 2004-2006, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 144)
    Correspondence between Pamela Gearhart and G. Schirmer concerning publication of works by Livingston Gearhart.
  - Gearhart, Lillian Hawley, 1889-1975: September 8, 1938, undated, 6 items (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Gearhart, Lynn Livingston, 1886-1966: November 20, 1955, January 15, 1956, 2 items (Box 3, Folder 146)
    Manuscripts accompanied by photograph of Lynn Livingston Gearhart in 1961.
  - Harberg, Margery: July 2, 1984, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Hutson, Wihla: 1960, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 148)
    Manuscripts and typescripts, including the score of the song, Christmas as it used to be, with words and music by Hutson.
  - Kiefer, Peter T.: 1996-1997, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 149)
    Manuscript and typescript notes between Peter Kiefer, for Penn State's Fred Waring's America collection, and Pamela Gearhart.
    Includes list of Livingston Gearhart's two-piano manuscripts in Penn State's collection.
  - Kimball, Patricia: December 17, 1996, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 150)
    Typescript note on behalf of the Buffalo Phillharmonic Orchestra.
    Includes manuscript list by Pamela Gearhart of Livingston Gearhart manuscripts believed to be held by the Buffalo Philharmonic Orchestra.
  - Kovach, Jules: November 15, 1996, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 151)
    Typescript addressed to Pamela Gearhart concerning Livingston manuscripts believed to be held by the Buffalo Philharmonic Orchestra.
  - Lawrence, Vera Brodsky: November 22, 1936, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - Lieberson, Goddard, 1911-1977: undated, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 153)
    Manuscript card inscribed with a melody and text.
  - Long, Marvin W.: December 11, 1980, 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 154)
    Typescript list of works by Livingston Gearhart held by the Fred Waring Music Library, with manuscript annotations.
  - Most, Anne: October 27, 1991, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 155)
    Manuscript letter accompanied by printed program for piano recital by Barbara Lewsi, May 4, 1923 in Buffalo, New York.
  - Motherwell, Robert: December 21, 1939, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 156)
  - Motherwell, Robert: May 21, 1942, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 157)
  - Motherwell, Robert: May 24, 1943, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 159)
    Manuscript with mention of meeting John Cage.
  - Motherwell, Robert: September 16, 1943, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 160)
  - Philipp, Isidore, 1863-1958: January 22, 1939, January 23, 1939, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 161)
  - Reese, Gustave, 1899-1977: February 15, 1937, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 162)
    Typescript on behalf of G. Schirner music publisher.
  - Schermerhorn, Martha: October 11, 1995, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 163)
  - Stegall, Joel R.: June 7, 1983, leaves (Box 3, Folder 164)
    Typescript list of Livingston Gearhhart works dontated to Ithaca College School of Music.
  - Tillstrom, Burr: December 17, 1949, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 165)
    Typescript from creator of Kukla, Fran and Ollie.
  - Torberg, Friedrich, 1908-1979: 1945, 3 items (3 leaves) (Box 3, Folder 166)
  - Valéry, François: July 26, 1939, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 167)
  - Valéry, Jeannie: June 6, 1939, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 168)
  - Waring, Fred, 1900-1984: May 7, 1945, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 169)
    Photocopy of typescript with annotation by Livingston Gearhart.
  - Waring, Paul Gearhart: undated, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 170)
    Manuscript from Livingston Gearhart to his son Paul.
  - Bogdan, N. A.: August 21, 1948, 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 171)
    Letterhead: "n.a.b."; reference in letter to being "Bogdanesque".
  - Unidentified surname, forename Alex: undated, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 172)
    Manuscript on Hotel Algonquin (New York, New York) letterhead.
  - Unidentified surname, forename Bill: September 8, 1993, June 1, 1996, undated, 6 leaves (Box 3, Folder 173)
    Manuscript and typescript notes written by Livingston Gearhart, addressed to "Bill".
  - Unidentified surname, forename Earl: undated, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 174)
    Manuscript note written by Livingston Gearhart, addressed to "Earl" concerning Gearhart's arrangement of We shall overcome.
  - Unidentified surname, forename John: March 31, 1994, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 175)
    Typescript note from "John" to Gearhart.
  - Unidentified surname, forenames Mildred and Lara: May 1, 1989, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 176)
    Typescript note from Livingston Gearhart to "Mildred and Lara".
  - Unidentified surname, forename Yoshio: Feburary 18, 1981, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 177)
    Manuscript note written by Livingston Gearhart, addressed to "Yoshio".
  - Unidentified correspondents: 1936-1940, 5 items (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - Correspondence regarding Livingston Gearhart's "Bass materials": 2002, 12 leaves (Box 4, Folder 179)
    Manuscript and typescript correspondence between Pamela Gearhart and correspondents.
  - Correspondence regarding Livingston Gearhart's "Rhythm sessions" and "Reading sessions": 1998-2000, 24 leaves (Box 4, Folder 180)
    Manuscript and typescript correspondence between Pamela Gearhart and correspondents, including proofreading lists.
  - Correspondence regarding Livingston Gearhart's "Sax sessions": 1997-2004, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 181)
- Additional programs, clippings, and publicity, 1932-2006, XII.; Folder 182-188
  - Clippings concerning the career of Livingston Gearhart, 1932-1963, 1 folder (Box 4, Item 182)
    Chiefly photocopies.
    Documentation includes clippings about early performances with his mother Lillian Hawley Gearhart and his sister, Martha.
  - Programs documenting performances of music by Livingston Gearhart, 1951-2006, 1 folder (Box 4, Item 183)
  - Programs documenting performances by the Morley and Gearhart piano duo, 1938-1953, 1 folder (Box 4, Item 184)
  - Publicity materials for the Morley and Gearhart piano duo, circa 1940-1953, 1 folder (Box 4, Item 185)
    Includes Press book created by Columbia Masterwork Records.
  - Clippings documenting performances by the Morley and Gearhart piano duo, circa 1940-1953, 1 folder (Box 4, Item 186)
  - Virginia Waring's synopsis of Morley and Gearhart piano duo performance at the White House on November 17, 1953: undated, 3 leaves (Box 4, Item 187)
  - Caricature of Livingston Gearhart by C. Brodine, undated, 1 leaf (Box 4, Item 188)
    Photocopy.
- Works lists, 1947-2005, XIII.; Folder 189-194
  - Catalog of works by Livingston Gearhart, circa 2005, 1 volume (Box 4, Item 189)
    Spiral bound inventory compiled by Pamela Gearhart, including some of her annotations.
  - Livingston Gearhart Seletced works list, undated, 1 leaf (Box 4, Item 190)
    Issued by Shawnee Press.
  - Manuscript lists of works by Livingston Gearhart published by Shawnee Press, undated, 1 folder (Box 4, Item 191)
    Compiled by Pamela Gearhart, including some sales figures.
  - LG wks: toward an archive, undated, 5 leaves (Box 4, Item 192)
    Typescript, including proposed filing system.
  - LG works in Ithaca storage, undated, 1 leaf (Box 4, Item 193)
    Manuscript list by Pamela Gearhart.
  - Contents listings of compilations by Livingston Gearhart, 1947-2000, 8 items (Box 4, Item 194)
    Photocopies.
    Bass clef sessions
    Clarinet sessions
    Fiddle sessions
    Flute sessions
    String mix
    Duet sessions
    Treble clef sessions
    Trumpet sessions
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Gearhart, Pamela; Waring, Virginia
Subjects
Boulanger, Nadia; Gearhart, Lillian Hawley, 1889-1975; Composers--New York (State)--Buffalo; Conservatoire américain de Fontainebleau; Morley and Gearhart; Curtis Institute of Music; Musicians
Genres
clippings (information artifacts); concert programs; correspondence
Associated Material
Separated Material
Photographs received with the collection were removed to form a separate collection, Mus. Arc. 23.3.
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Livingston Gearhart Collection of Scores, 1930-1996
Mus. Arc. 23.2
Extensive collection (26 boxes) of manuscript and published scores composed or arranged by Livingston Gearhart. Also includes published scores of other composers as annotated by Gearhart.
Livingston Gearhart Collection of Photographs,1896-1941
Mus. Arc. 23.3
Collection of 192 images, including photographs of Nadia Boulanger and her summer class of 1938, Gearhart and his first wife, Virginia Morley (Waring) at Mills College in California, with composer Darius Milhaud and his family, and the Budapest String Quartet. The collection also includes four photographs of composer Johannes Brahms in 1896. Also available as a digital collection in
University Libraries Digital Collections
.
Livingston Gearhart Recordings, 1949-2001
Mus. Arc. 23.4
Collection of 24 recordings, including compositions and arrangements by Livingston Gearhart, his memorial service, and the recordings of duo-pianists, Morley and Gearhart.
Related Resources at Other Institutions
Fred Waring's America Collection
Pennsylvania State University's collection of material related to the Fred Waring shows, including some of Livingston Gearhart's arrangements.